<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Quartz.NET | Minasss Projects Dump Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://html5dev.altervista.org//blog/categories/quartz-net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://html5dev.altervista.org//"/>
  <updated>2013-03-21T15:34:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://html5dev.altervista.org//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Francesco Pischedda]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring distributed calculation with RabbitMQ]]></title>
    <link href="http://html5dev.altervista.org//posts/2013/02/28/exploring-distributed-calculation-with-rabbitmq/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-28T19:22:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://html5dev.altervista.org//posts/2013/02/28/exploring-distributed-calculation-with-rabbitmq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Preface</h1>

<p>Lately I've had to work on a complex web application which have started to have
an increased (and increasing) number of users. Unfortunately this web
application was not built to scale easily and so problems started to get to the
surface.
When the user base was small to medium the load on the application server
was fairly low and we could focus on adding new features and growing our
user base until we landed on the Facebook platform. At some point users started
to came and the scheduled task took 10-20-40-70-90 minutues to complete leaving
the users to stare at the "calculating tasks" page.</p>

<p>The first approved solution was to migrate our servers to AWS so we could
increase host perfomance using bigger and bigger servers until we reached the
limits of the single machines again.</p>

<p>After a lot of battling with the management we had the opportunity to detach
the application core from the web site and started to build the new
architecture with these loosely defined requirements:</p>

<ul>
<li>better use of resources</li>
<li>better code organization and quality</li>
<li>horizontal scaling</li>
<li>manageabilty</li>
<li>ready for future development</li>
</ul>


<p>I admit that those where my requirements, but the management undestood that
they have lost the ability to understand the architecture beyhond a simple web
site with a bounch of scheduled routines that, honestly, worked with the help
of an infinite dose of luck...and also my prototype run in a fraction of time.</p>

<h1>Building blocks</h1>

<p>Our old backend has been broken in to those pieces:</p>

<ul>
<li>libcore : the base code extracted from the old and stinky web site</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rabbitmq.com">RabbitMQ</a> message broker</li>
<li>job scheduler : send messages to appropriate exchanges at appropriate time</li>
<li>workers : consume messages sent by the scheduler</li>
</ul>


<p>Leaving libcore apart doing its stuff lets focus on the scheduler and the
workers; for details about RabbitMQ please refer to its <a href="http://www.rabbitmq.com">web site</a>.</p>

<p>As a scheduling library I have choosen the open source
<a href="http://quartznet.sourceforge.net/">Quartz.NET</a> which provided a simple but
powerful interface to schedule jobs, I especially liked the ability to specify job
triggers with the well known and compact cron syntax. Long story short the
scheduled jobs harvests the tasks and send messages to exchanges accordingly.
I think that the whole core plus the jobs are not bigger than some hundreds of
lines of code. Wonderful!</p>

<p>The workers simply have to inherit from a BaseConsumer class and override the
consume method to do its tasks when a message is received. Done. Cool :)</p>

<p>Given this simple architecture what are the benefits? Lets see:</p>

<ul>
<li>scaling: I simply have to add more workers in the same or different machines
and the calculating power will increase accordingly</li>
<li>flexibility: if a new task is required I have to create a new scheduled job
and its consumer and maybe a new message type (messages are simple JSON
described objects); after all is tested I have to update the scheduler and add a
new worker either by updating a running worker or adding a new one without
affecting the whole system; yes it can be done while the system is crunching
its task and yes, obviously without affecting the web site(s)</li>
<li>cost effective: if we have a lot of task to complete at a certain hour in the
day I could simply turn on a couple of more machines when I need it and turn
those off when the whole work is completed; if you have ever used the Amazon
AWS infrastructure you understand of much one can save using this approach</li>
<li>testing: having everything well separated I can test each block individually
instead of having a code blob that is barely manageable</li>
</ul>


<p>With this short post I hope to increase interest in this simple way of doing
distribuited computing using a message broker (whatever its is) and a simple
but well architected system.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
