<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: development | Minasss Projects Dump Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://html5dev.altervista.org//blog/categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://html5dev.altervista.org//"/>
  <updated>2013-03-21T15:34:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://html5dev.altervista.org//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Francesco Pischedda]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim: My new portable IDE]]></title>
    <link href="http://html5dev.altervista.org//posts/2013/01/08/my-new-portable-ide/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T17:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://html5dev.altervista.org//posts/2013/01/08/my-new-portable-ide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Why</h2>

<p>In the last six months I've felt the need to explore the command line ecosystem
of development tools and I've inevitably started to learn (ehm, again)
<a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a> and then <a href="http://www.vim.org">Vim</a>,
the latter have won the battle. I liked Emacs but I ended up using Vim, I think
it's just a matter of taste and I really don't understand those famouse flame
wars between the two user groups :)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>After I've found my editor of choice I've had to start filling it with the best
plugins for my development needs and thanks to this
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YhqsjUUHj6g">video</a>
now I have a very powerfull IDE that takes up little resources, is easily
extendable with tons of plugins and you can really write at speed of thought!</p>

<p>To get in the Vim philosofy doesn't take too much time, just start to hack some
of your code, learn what keys you need to get that specific feature
(autocompletition for example) and repeat until you feel confortable, I think
that in a week or two one can became a Vim power user.</p>

<p>In the title I've used the word "portable", why? And why is so important to me?
Well, I think Vim is available for near every OS out there and that's a good
thing by itself but adding the fact that you can have an exact replica of your
preferred plugins and settings by simply copying around your .vim directory is,
in my opinion, awesome! For example last week I've had the need to use Vim on a
remote machine, at its first start it was the plain old Vim (Ubuntu 11.10
stock version) but after an scp I felt like it was my local development
machine.</p>

<p>There is a lot to learn to become a Vim guru but fortunately there are lot of
free resources out there to get you familiar with Vim, let me point out some:</p>

<ul>
<li>vim tutor: built in with vim, very useful tutorial to get started</li>
<li>vim :help command</li>
<li>this video <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YhqsjUUHj6g">tutorial</a> on how to build
vim from scratch with python support, also has some nice keybindings and Vim
tips</li>
<li><a href="http://vimcasts.org/">VimCasts</a>, a lot of useful material about Vim</li>
<li>Google about Vim :)</li>
</ul>


<p>Even if not free (but very affordable) I strongly suggest the book
<a href="http://pragprog.com/book/dnvim/practical-vim">Pratical Vim</a> by Drew Neil,
the same author of the VimCasts web site.</p>

<h2>Closing Considerations</h2>

<p>Probably someone new to this topic will ask "why have I to learn a new set of
key bindings or use the terminal with my new shiny and powerful computer
when there are tons of good graphical IDEs with lots of buttons and menus?"</p>

<p>My very personal answer is that when you learn all this new stuff you will
probably be more and more productive or at least that's what happened to me.
Again, it's a matter of taste, but it won't kill you if you give it a try,
trust me :)</p>

<p>I know that I'm far away from the status of Vim guru but learning is a fun
process and while I'm doing it I'm also producing useful code so there is no
waste here.</p>

<p>Talking about learning I'm going to read this nice
<a href="http://blog.sanctum.geek.nz/advanced-vim-registers/">article</a> about Vim's
registers :)</p>

<h2>Footnotes</h2>

<p>This post has been written using Vim + <a href="https://github.com/hallison/vim-markdown">vim-markdown</a>
plugin in a <a href="http://tmux.sourceforge.net/">tmux</a> session running Vim in one pane
and <a href="http://octopress.org/">octopress</a> in the other.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
